Finding Aid for Griswold family papers [microform], 1837-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Griswold family papers [microform] 1837-1915
Griswold family
1 linear foot, 1 reel microfilm
851377 Aa 2
Vermontville, Michigan, family. Civil War correspondence and diaries of Joseph B. Griswold, musician in the Second Michigan Cavalry, and later Assistant Surgeon in the Fourth Michigan Infantry; also material concerning the land transactions of Roger W. Griswold; and miscellaneous clippings, photograph, correspondence, and printed material.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan (donor no. 1278 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research. Access to the microfilm copy only.
The originals of the microfilmed papers are located at the Bentley Historical Library.
The Griswold family were early settlers to Vermontville, Michigan. One family member, Roger W. Griswold, was proprietor of a farm and general store in Vermontville in the mid-nineteenth century. Another, Joseph B. Griswold (born 1842) attended Vermontville Academy and entered Michigan Agricultural College in 1858. He enlisted in the Second Michigan Cavalry in August 1861. He was discharged one year later because of a disability. After recovering, he attended the University of Michigan Department of Medicine and Surgery, 1863-1864, then re-enlisted as an assistant surgeon with the Fourth Michigan Infantry. He rose to the rank of Major and became Medical Inspector of the Department of San Antonio and had medical charge of the military prison there. After the war, he entered Rush Medical College, graduating in February 1868. He practiced medicine in Minnesota for six years, then in 1874 moved to Grand Rapids.
The Griswold family papers includes materials for both Roger W. and Joseph B. Griswold. The bulk of the collection consists of letters, diaries, and other materials of Joseph B. Griswold relating to his Civil War service.
Subjects:
Griswold family.; Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States. Michigan Commandery.; Musicians--Michigan--Vermontville.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1864-1866); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Vermontville (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Grand Army of the Republic--Michigan.; Griswold, Joseph Bascom, 1842-1915.; Veterans--Michigan.
Contributors:
Griswold, Joseph Bascom, 1842-1915.; Griswold, Roger W., 1812-1886.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Family papers
  - Papers, 1863-1915 and undated (Reel 1)
    (include biographical material on Roger W. Griswold and Joseph B. Griswold,)
  - Papers, 1837-1878 (Reel 1)
    (include indentures and deeds for land transactions of Roger W. Griswold)
  - Papers, 1855-1886 (Reel 1)
    ( include business records and tax receipts of Roger W. Griswold)
  - Correspondence, 1855-1858 and undated (Reel 1)
    (include letters from Abigail Griswold (Mrs. Roger W. Griswold) to her daughter Hattie attending the Female College in Lansing)
  - Correspondence, 1862-1866 (Reel 1)
    (include letters from Dr. Joseph B. Griswold to his sister, Hattie Griswold Bacon, concerning his service in the Civil War)
  - Diaries of Dr. Joseph B. Griswold concerning his service in the Civil War, 1861-1862 and 1865 (Reel 1)
  - Papers concerning the service of Dr. Joseph Griswold in the Civil War, 1861-1866 (Reel 1)
  - Booklet entitled "The Soldier's Pocket Book " put out by the Presbyterian Board of Education, 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Papers concerning the membership of Dr. Joseph B. Griswold in military organizations (i.e. G.A.R.), 1885-1914 (Reel 1)
  - Papers include appointments and commissions of Dr. Joseph B. Griswold, 1882-1911 (Reel 1)
    (signed by Michigan governors)
  - Correspondence, 1894-1895 (Reel 1)
    (include letters of Dr. Joseph B. Griswold and William McKinley and Benjamin Harrison)
  - Campaign material, 1896 (Reel 1)
    (include songs by Joseph B. Griswold; also pamphlet published by the Sound Money League)
  - Booklets, "Songs of the Ohio Commandery" and "War Songs" 1885 and 1890 (Reel 1)
  - Book of remembrance belonging to Mrs. Joseph B. Griswold, undated (Reel 1)
  - Printed materials, 1876-1914 (Reel 1)
  - Photograph of the Past Department Commanders of the G.A.R of Michigan, 1907 (Reel 1)